"Using Thylakoids to Suppress
Hunger and Boost GLP-1"
The cells that produce
the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
in response to calorie exposure
are concentrated
all the way down
at the end
of our digestive tract,
which is why our appetites
are not suppressed very much
these days.
The majority
of the calories we eat
are absorbed early
in our digestive tract;
so, they never make it down
far enough.
When we eat a donut,
its fat, sugar, and starch
get absorbed quickly, high up,
before reaching the part
of our digestive tract
where we produce
most of the hormone
that suppresses our appetite.
So, from a GLP-1 standpoint,
it’s like we never ate
much of anything.
No wonder we reach for donut #2.
How can we eat a donut
and still get GLP-1 activation?
Surgery!
Bariatric surgery
can involve cutting out
part of our small intestine
so some of the donut calories
may reach the end of it
after all.
What if you want to eat a donut,
still get GLP-1 activation,
and keep your anatomy intact?
Drugs!
By injecting GLP-1
mimicking drugs, like Ozempic,
you can get GLP-1 activation
no matter what you eat.
You could also take
the starch-blocker drug acarbose
to slow the digestion
of carbohydrates,
or the fat-blocker drug orlistat
to slow the digestion of fats.
But what if you want
GLP-1 activation
without drugs or surgery?
Well, you could try
not eating donuts.
Ancestral humans
might have consumed
as much as 100 grams
of fiber daily.
That’s about six times
what most of us are getting
these days.
We evolved eating massive
amounts of whole plant foods,
the only place
fiber is found in abundance.
So, by eating
the way nature intended,
we can release GLP-1
which helps explain why
a whole food, plant-based diet
is one of the most powerful
weight loss interventions
ever published.
But what do we do
about our cravings?
What are some
therapeutic approaches
to addressing them?
Well, there are drugs,
of course,
but in terms
of food-based interventions,
there are thylakoids,
which are just the
chlorophyll-rich membranes
inside leaves where
photosynthesis takes place.
Thylakoids act as fat blockers,
delaying our digestion of fats
and promoting the release
of satiety hormones like GLP-1.
When we eat thylakoids,
in other words, when we bite
into a leaf of spinach,
for instance,
the thylakoid membranes
are able to resist
our digestive enzymes.
They can last for hours
in our gut
before finally
being broken down,
and it is in those hours
when they work their magic.
Thylakoids glom
onto tiny droplets of fat
in our digestive tract,
and, in this way,
powerfully slow our digestion
of fat.
And that means more GLP-1.
Yes, GLP-1 is a hormone
that is being developed
as an anti-obesity drug
(this was published two years
before Ozempic).
But thylakoids
can cause our natural,
endogenous release of GLP-1,
which is an easier
and more physiological way
to enhance GLP-1 levels
to achieve satiety
and calorie balance.
But does it
actually cut cravings?
Spinach extracts
were disguised in jam and juice
to sneak thylakoids
undetected into meals,
and those unwittingly eating
the equivalent
of about half a cup (100 g)
of cooked spinach
felt significantly less hungry
and more satiated
over the next few hours.
Give someone the equivalent
of a shot of wheatgrass juice
or what they might get
in a "green drink"
or green smoothie,
and not only do they feel
more satiated,
but their cravings for sweet,
salty, and fatty snacks,
such as potato chips,
chocolate, and cinnamon buns,
drop by about a third.
Feed them candy anyway,
and those who unknowingly
had been snuck some spinach,
report liking the sweets
significantly less.
The satiating power of greens
has been attributed
to their high fiber
and water contents
and low calorie density,
but the thylakoids
may be their secret weapon,
presumably because of
the increased release of GLP-1
following
thylakoid supplementation.
In a systematic review
of randomized controlled trials
on the effects
of thylakoid intake
on appetite and weight loss,
hunger-suppressing effects
of thylakoids
were reported in all studies
that directly measured
hunger and fullness.
But what about the weight loss?
Would the GLP-induced reduction
of cravings and hunger
from greens
translate into losing pounds?
That’s what I’ll cover next.